A Finding Aid to the Minna Wright Citron Papers, 1930-1980, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Minna Wright Citron papers
1930-1980
Archives of American Art
Citron, Minna Wright, 1896-1991
AAA.citrminn
Archival Resource Key
1.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker and muralist Minna Wright Citron measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1980. Found are scattered biographical materials, correspondence, writings for articles and lectures, printed material, photographs, and artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 97 and 268 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Related Materials
Syracuse University also holds the Minna Citron papers, 1932-2014.
Biographical / Historical
Painter and printmaker Minna Wright Citron (1896-1991) was active in New York City, New York. She worked with the Works Progress Administration Federal Art Project as a teacher and completed multiple murals for Tennessee post offices.
Born in Newark, New Jersey, Minna Wright Citron began her study of art at the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences in 1924. She juggled the work of raising two small sons, a husband, and her art career and had her first solo exhibition in 1930 at New School for Social Research. In 1934, she divorced her husband Henry Citron and moved her children, Casper and Thomas, from Brooklyn to Manhattan.
Citron spent her early career as a painter, muralist, and educator. After World War II, she began to experiment with printmaking techniques and produced woodblock prints, etchings, and lithographs. She exhibited her works around the world, notably in Zagreb, Croatia (formerly Yugoslavia).
Minna Wright Citron died in 1991.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Minna Wright Citron donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in several installments from 1968 to 1981.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, printmaker and muralist Minna Wright Citron measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1980. Found are scattered biographical materials, correspondence, writings for articles and lectures, printed material, photographs, and artwork.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Women printmakers; Women educators; Drawings
- Minna Wright Citron papers, 1930-1980; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include short biographical sketches, resumes, and printed pamphlets for Casper Citron's run for the United States House of Representatives.
  Correspondence is with family, friends, and colleagues. Letters from the 1940s discuss her murals in Newport and Manchester, Tennessee. Other correspondents include the American Color Print Society and the U.S. Department of State which helped to organize her international exhibitions. Also found are typescripts of letters Citron wrote to family while in Paris in 1947.
  Writings include notes and outlines for lectures and articles on art by Citron. Printed materials include many exhibition announcements and catalogs for her exhibitions in the United States and abroad, some of which are annotated. There are portraits and snapshots of Citron and of Citron with her art, as well as photographs of events, family, friends, exhibitions, studio spaces, and Citron's artwork. Also found are pencil sketches, ink sketches, an etching, a woodblock print, and two lithographs.
  - Biographical Material, 1940-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
  - Correspondence, Typescripts of Letters from Paris, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings and Notes, Lectures, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Writings and Notes, Articles by Minna Wright Citron, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings and Notes, Articles by Others, 1949-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Contract, Lafayette College, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - Photographs of Minna Wright Citron, 1940s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Minna Wright Citron with Friends and Family, 1930s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions and Studio, 1940-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, Etching, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Artwork, Sketches, circa 1940-circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artwork, Oversized Woodcut and Lithographs, 1939-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)